Hi, this is Matt Baker. Earlier this
year, I did a video on the US TV and
film industry, showing how various
companies have merged over time. Well,
today I'm going to do the same thing for
the music industry, focusing on major
record labels and how these two have
been consolidated in recent decades.
We're going to start up here with the
invention of the gramophone by Emile
Berliner in the late 1800s. Previous to
this, Thomas Edison had invented the
phonograph, but that was slightly
different in that the phonograph used
cylinders, whereas the gramophone used
flat discs, eventually known as records.
Berliner's discs were easier to
mass-produce, so pretty soon the
gramophone became the primary device
used for playing music. Initially, the
E. Berliner Gramophone Company was the
only company to produce records, but
because of weak patents, pretty soon
other companies started making them as
well. Their first big competitor was the
Columbia Phonograph Company, which, as
their name suggests, started out by
selling phonograph cylinders, but then
switched to gramophone records around
1901. Take note, however, that over
time, the words phonograph and
gramophone basically became synonymous
with both words eventually referring to
record players.
Because of lawsuits, Berliner was forced
to close his original business in the US
and transfer his assets to a new company
called the Victor Talking Machine
Company. However, in the UK, he was able
to carry on as the Gramophone Company.
Both firms ended up using the same logo,
based on a now-famous painting called
His Master's Voice, featuring a dog
named Nipper listening to a gramophone.
In the UK, the Gramophone Company opened
stores called His Master's Voice, which
was later simplified to HMV. To this
day, HMV stores often feature the old
logo with Nipper. Another very early
record company originally based out of
Germany was Parlophone. It's famous for
being the label that the Beatles were
initially associated with. You might
assume that their logo represents the
British pound symbol, but it's actually
a stylized L standing for Carl
Lindstrom, the company's founder. In
1926, long before the Beatles were
signed, Parlophone was actually bought
by the UK branch of Columbia, which had
become independent from the US branch
just a few years earlier. But then in
1931, UK Columbia merged with UK
Gramophone to become Electric and
Musical Industries, better known as EMI.
For the next 80 years, EMI would be the
number one record company in the UK,
continuing to use the Columbia,
Parlophone, and HMV labels.
EMI's main competition there ended up
being Decca, established in London in
1929. Take note, however, that Decca
also started an American branch, which
soon became independent. Which brings me
back to the US.
You see, in 1929, which is the year that
Emile Berliner died, the Victor Talking
Machine Company was bought by the Radio
Corporation of America, or RCA, which
also owned NBC. Meanwhile, about a
decade later, NBC's main competitor,
CBS, bought Columbia. So, by the 1940s,
America had three big record companies:
RCA Victor, CBS Columbia, and US Decca.
Now, before I continue, I want to shout
out today's sponsor, Ground News, which
is the website and app that I use to
follow the news. Not just politics, but
fun stuff, too, like the announcement of
the Rolling Stones new album. What
Ground News does is pull headlines from
hundreds of different sources from all
over the world, including newspapers,
podcasts, and websites. It then
categorizes them on a continuum from
left to right, so that you get to look
at the story from different angles. So,
even when it comes to something as
simple as The Rolling Stones releasing a
new album, you can see how the spin is
often different. For example, this
left-leaning source emphasized the
collaborative nature of the album,
whereas this right-leaning source
emphasized the age of the band. Of
course, the best thing about Ground News
is the charts, such as this one showing
the bias distribution, or this one
showing which sources are the most
factual based on third-party rankings,
or this one showing what percentage of
the sources are independently owned, or
owned by the government or big business.
Ground News also has a blind spot feed,
which highlights stories that one side
of the spectrum is barely covering at
all. So, you're not just trapped inside
the version of events your usual media
bubble wants to feed you. So, don't
wait. Subscribe now by going to
ground.news/charts,
or by using the link in the description
or pinned comment. If you use that
address or link, you will get 40% off
unlimited access to their Vantage plan.
Again, that's ground.news/charts.
Okay, let's now return to the timeline
of major record labels. We left off in
the 1940s, when the US had just three
main record companies: RCA Victor, home
of big band conductor Glenn Miller; CBS
Columbia, home of early teen idol Frank
Sinatra; and Decca, home of actor,
dancer, and singer Bing Crosby. Now, at
this point, most records were made of
shellac, which was very brittle and set
to spin at 78 RPMs. But then, in 1948,
Columbia introduced the very first vinyl
records, which spun at around 33 RPMs
and were called LPs, or long plays,
meaning that they could hold around five
songs on each side. This was then
followed in 1949 by RCA Victor
introducing a new single format in vinyl
that spun at 45 RPMs. This is why record
players to this day usually have three
settings: 33, 45, and 78 so that you can
play all of these different types of
records. Sometimes there's a fourth
setting, 16, which is used for spoken
word only.
Anyhow, the introduction of vinyl and
the LP kick-started a new era of music,
which I've labeled the vinyl era, in
which musicians now release singles as
well as full albums, which usually had
around 10 songs. This coincided with the
birth of rock and roll, the first really
big star being of course Elvis Presley,
who was initially signed by a relatively
minor label called Sun, but then later
picked up by RCA Victor.
In 1955, EMI, which remember was a
British label, bought Capitol Records,
making them their primary distributor in
the US. Thus, by the 1960s, there were
now four major record companies in the
US: RCA, which eventually dropped the
Victor name, Columbia, Capitol, and
Decca. Columbia eventually became the
top US label thanks to artists like Bob
Dylan and Johnny Cash, with number two
being Capitol, which distributed the
Beatles. Although, like I mentioned
earlier in the UK, the Beatles started
out on EMI's Parlophone label. Later,
they started their own label called
Apple.
There were lots of other labels though,
too many to list on this chart. But, let
me point out several other important
ones that were founded during the vinyl
era, starting with Atlantic Records,
which originally focused on soul,
launching the career of Aretha Franklin.
Elektra Records, which launched The
Doors, and Reprise Records, which was
started by Frank Sinatra. All three of
these were eventually bought by Warner
Brothers Records, which as you can
probably guess was started by the Warner
Brothers film studio. Now, at this
point, Warner Records became known as
Warner Electra Atlantic, or WEA, and it
went on to become the fifth major record
company in the US, representing big
names such as Led Zeppelin and The
Eagles.
Now, during the 1970s, there also ended
up being a sixth major company,
PolyGram. So, let me go back a bit and
tell you where it came from. Back in
1913, a German company launched a label
called Polydor. Then, during World War
I, it acquired the German branch of
Berliner's Gramophone Company, which
incidentally allowed it to use the His
Master's Voice logo in Germany.
Eventually, the whole thing was bought
by the German conglomerate Siemens.
Meanwhile, in the Netherlands, the Dutch
conglomerate Philips started its own
record label. It then bought Mercury
Records in the US and rebranded as
Phonogram. So, you had Polydor in
Germany and Phonogram in the
Netherlands. These two companies started
to work together in the '60s and joined
officially in the '70s to create
PolyGram. Poly from Polydor and Gram
from Phonogram.
Okay, before we leave the vinyl era, I
want to point out a few more important
independent labels, such as Island
Records, which distributed Bob Marley,
A&M Records, which launched The
Carpenters, and Motown, which was
founded by Berry Gordy, whose family
tree I've covered on this channel.
Motown was really important in that it
was the first African-American owned
label to become super popular with white
audiences, coinciding with the Civil
Rights era in the US. It launched lots
of famous artists such as Marvin Gaye,
Diana Ross, Stevie Wonder, and the
Jackson 5. Now, the reason why I show
these three labels together is because
they were all eventually bought by
PolyGram. All right, we've now made it
to the 1980s, which is when the vinyl
era came to an end. This was due to the
rise of the cassette tape, which ended
up surpassing vinyl in terms of sales
around the year 1985. But, the reason
why we don't have a cassette tape era is
because cassettes were surpassed within
less than a decade by compact discs, or
CDs. Now, during the '80s, '90s, and
early 2000s, there continued to be six
big record companies, but in several
cases, there were some big changes in
terms of ownership. So, let me now go
through the big six again and tell you
what happened. Warner Elektra Atlantic
continued to be really successful in the
'80s, representing artists such as
Madonna and Metallica. And then, as we
learned in the TV and Film episode, in
1991, Warner became Time Warner, at the
time the biggest media conglomerate in
the world. But, one thing I didn't
mention in that video was Time Warner's
disastrous merger with the internet
company AOL, which led to its decline.
One of the results of that decline was
that the music side of the business was
sold. And thus, from 2004 onwards,
Warner Music has been totally separate
from Warner Entertainment, even though
they still share the same name. Warner
Music now uses this logo, whereas Warner
Entertainment still uses the original
Warner Brothers logo. Now, Warner
Brothers was not the only film studio to
start its own record label. Columbia
Pictures started one as well in 1974
called Arista Records. It launched
Whitney Houston, but soon thereafter
Arista was bought by a German company
called Bertelsmann, which continued to
record her music. Now, earlier I
mentioned that RCA was not only the
owners of a record company, but also of
NBC, by now a major TV network. Well, in
1986, when RCA was bought by General
Electric, the new owners decided to keep
the TV channel, but ditch the record
company. At this point, Bertelsmann
bought RCA and formed BMG, which stands
for Bertelsmann Music Group. BMG went on
to buy Jive Records, the home of Britney
Spears and N Sync, and thus ended up
having a massive catalog of artists,
both old and new.
Next up is Columbia, which, as I
mentioned earlier, was the number one
record company in the US throughout the
vinyl era. Well, during the 1980s, it
kept this number one spot thanks to
being the home of Michael Jackson.
Although, take note that Jackson
actually used one of their subsidiary
labels, Epic Records. Now, remember
Columbia Records was owned by the TV
network CBS. Well, around the same time
that NBC parted ways with RCA Records,
CBS parted ways with Columbia Records,
selling their entire music business to
the Japanese conglomerate Sony, who, as
we learned in the TV and film episode,
also bought Columbia Pictures. So, to
this day, Columbia Records and Columbia
Pictures are now owned by the same
company. But then, in 2008, Sony also
bought BMG, giving Sony Music four major
labels, Columbia, RCA, Arista, and Epic,
among many others.
We're now going to skip past Capitol EMI
for a moment and go straight to US
Decca, which in 1952 acquired Universal
Pictures, a fact that will become
important in a moment. But first, you
need to know that in 1962,
Decca, which now included Universal, was
bought by MCA, which stands for Music
Corporation of America. Initially, MCA
continued to use the Decca label, but
then rebranded as MCA Records in 1972.
Their biggest star at that time was
Elton John. However, it was during the
'90s that MCA, which eventually
rebranded itself again, this time as
Universal Music Group, really started to
grow, swallowing up all sorts of
independent labels, as well as one
really big one. First off, there was
Geffen Records, which launched Guns N'
Roses, and Interscope, which distributed
major rappers such as Dr. Dre, Snoop
Dogg, and Tupac. But then, in 1998,
Universal bought all of PolyGram, which,
remember, came with Motown, Island, and
a bunch of other labels, including a
newer one called Def Jam, whose very
first artist was LL Cool J.
So, with the merger of Universal and
PolyGram, Universal was now the biggest
record company in the world, as well as,
of course, a major film studio. However,
in the same year that Warner Pictures
and Warner Music split up, so did
Universal Pictures and Universal Music.
Universal Pictures was bought by General
Electric and combined with NBC, whereas
Universal Music continued on as a
totally separate entity, even though, to
this day, they share very similar logos.
I now want to return to the UK for a
moment, where, as I mentioned, EMI was
the dominant force. Well, another
British label of note is Virgin, started
by Richard Branson in 1972.
Today, Virgin operates lots of
companies, including an airline and even
a space tourism outfit. However, it no
longer operates the business it started
with, Virgin Records, because it sold
that to EMI in 1992.
But, 20 years later, EMI itself was sold
to Universal. The only two things that
that deal did not include were the HMV
stores, because those became independent
in '98, and Parlophone, which went to
Warner instead. Although, take note that
Universal kept the rights to distribute
the Beatles.
So, by the time streaming took over CD
sales around 2015, there were only three
main music companies in the entire
English-speaking world: Warner, Sony,
and Universal. These days, Warner
represents Ed Sheeran, and Sony
distributes Bad Bunny. But, most of the
biggest names in the music business are
with Universal. For example, Taylor
Swift, The Weeknd, and Ariana Grande are
all signed with Republic Records, which
Universal bought in 2000. And Billie
Eilish, Kendrick Lamar, and Lady Gaga
are all represented by Interscope, now
also known as Interscope Geffen A&M. So,
just like we saw in the TV and film
episode, the pattern is small fish
getting eaten up by bigger fish with
fewer and fewer big fish as time goes
on.
Okay, let me know in the comments who
your favorite music artist is, and what
label they are currently signed to. And
don't forget to check out Ground News.
Thanks for watching.
>> Mhm.